<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to sundry matters contain'd in Mr. Hunt's postscript to his argument for the bishops right in judging capital causes in Parliament ... whereunto is added a query to be put to the scrupulous and dissenting brotherhood : with an advertisement how usurpers of the crown ought to be dealt with / by Wa. Williams of the Middle Temple, a barrister at law.</title>
            <author>Williams, Walter, of the Middle Temple.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66454</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2773A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17291031</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17291031</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106342</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66454)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1163:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to sundry matters contain'd in Mr. Hunt's postscript to his argument for the bishops right in judging capital causes in Parliament ... whereunto is added a query to be put to the scrupulous and dissenting brotherhood : with an advertisement how usurpers of the crown ought to be dealt with / by Wa. Williams of the Middle Temple, a barrister at law.</title>
                  <author>Williams, Walter, of the Middle Temple.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Charles Harper and are to be sold by Walter Davis ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with print show-through and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hunt, Thomas, 1627?-1688. --  Postscript for rectifying some mistakes in some of the inferiour clergy.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops --  Temporal power.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106342:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106342:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER To ſundry Matters contain'd in Mr. <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NT</hi>'S Poſtſcript, To His <hi>Argument, For the Biſhops Right in judging Capital Cauſes in</hi> PARLIAMENT. <hi>VIZ.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. As to his publiſhing a ſcandalous LETTER of the Clergy.</item>
                  <item>2. As to his wrongfully charging His Majeſty with neglect of the LAW, if he call'd not a Parliament once a year.</item>
                  <item>3. As to his falſe Affirmations, that the Succeſſion of the CROWN is the Peoples Right; and that not only the Line of Succeſſion, but Monarchy it ſelf may be alter'd.</item>
               </list> Whereunto is added A Query to be put to the Scrupulous and Diſſenting Brotherhood. WITH An Advertiſement, how Uſurpers of the Crown, ought to be dealt with. By <hi>Wa. Williams</hi> of the Middle Temple, a Barriſter at <hi>LAW</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Si Deus nobiſcum quis contra nos.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Charles Harper,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Walter Davis</hi> at <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106342:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106342:2"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT Antepoſited.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <hi>Had a long time ſince framed this enſuing Anſwer to y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> moſt celebrated Poſtſcript, but having done it, the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the wiſe Kings Advice,</hi> Anſwer not a Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>and</hi> Anſwer a Fool, <hi>wrought ſuch a Conflict within <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as hindred my ſending it; until of late I found by your w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Defence of the Charter, that you were become wiſe in y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> own Conceit; Therefore to indeavour to move that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper in your ſelf, and to undeceive ſuch as may be in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with the State-Hereſie, I at length Reſolved to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it, in hopes it may effect your and their Reformation, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> is deſired by</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W.W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:106342:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106342:3"/>
            <head>TO <hi>THOMAS H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NT,</hi> Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving occaſion lately to paſs through ſeveral parts of the Kingdom, and in my Journies, diſcourſing with ſeveral Gentlemen, that had been Members of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, in ſome of our late Parliaments, concerning the late Bill of Excluſion of His Royal Highneſs from the Succeſſion of the Crown; I found ſome of them, who once had no great opinion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the neceſſity, nor honeſty of that Bill, begin to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſome favourable thoughts of it; and that which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd them to it, as I was inform'd, was the powerful Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they met with in a very ingenious Piece (as they term'd it) call'd Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi>'s Poſtſcript, which was in great plenty very induſtriouſly diſperſed about by ſome <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true-Proteſtants,</hi> and magnified by them equally with, if not above the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>This great Character, and the mighty Effects it had wrought, ſet my Curioſity upon enquiry after this ſublime Fabrick of Politicks, but having found it; I muſt tell you without Complement, it proved a mere heap of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſcandalous Rubbiſh, ſituate like the Firebrands in the Tails of <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Foxes, tacked to the hinder end of a plauſible thing, <hi>viz.</hi> Your Argument for the Biſhops Right, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Your ſelf ſuſpecting (as I gueſs by the matter of it) that it had never found the way into our ſtanding
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106342:4"/>Corn, without the help of ſome ſuch Fox-like trick; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtuffed with nothing but Railings, falſe Recitals of Scripture Hiſtory, Fallacies and Chicaneries; which in plain Engliſh, are nothing but ſubtle impertinent quirks and quillets.</p>
            <p>Firſt, you act the ſlanderer by Proxie, and as I apprehend it, you feign a Letter from a Friend, containing very ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous things of the Clergie; amongſt the reſt, <hi>page</hi> the 2d. belying them, that they are all for a Popiſh Succeſſor, and no Parliament, and that they do as much as in them lies, give up our ancient Government, the Proteſtant Religion, the true Chriſtian Faith, to the abſolute will of a Popiſh Succeſſor; wherein you have done extreamly ill, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, you have declared your own opinion, that you believe that there are but few of them guilty of that charge; for your ſuppoſed Letter hath deeply wounded their Reputation with the credulous People, and given them too great an occaſion to hunt after Conventicles in ſearch for, ſuppoſed more Godly Teachers; and I dare affirm it, that your declaring your own opinion of them, is but a very ineffectual Plaiſter for their broken Heads, Whether you could have Argued better for them or not, I cannot ſay; but if you could not, your inability will no more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe you, than it did the young Conjurer that raiſed the Devil, but could not lay him; and though you would father the Lye upon another, I conceive however, that you have committed an Offence againſt the Statutes of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the firſt and the 2d. of <hi>R.</hi> 2. Touching Repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of falſe News, whereby ſlander may ariſe to the Biſhops of this Realm, for by Clergy is underſtood the Biſhops, as well as the inferiour Miniſters: your Friends tale being the moſt ſcandalous thing that could have been invented, and moſt likely to make the People hate all the Orthodox and Conformable Clergie in the Nation; for which I wiſh you your condign Puniſhment.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106342:4"/>
            <p>Another matter, you have taken great pains in <hi>page</hi> 29. of the Poſtſcript, and thereabouts, is to repreſent to the World, a Statute as in force, which is Repealed, and by Colour thereof, you take the freedom to aſperſe even His Majeſty himſelf; for you ſay that by the Statutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d. Parliaments are to be holden every Year; and thar the Statute of this King requires a Parliament every three Years; which as you ſay, being an affirmatory Law, doth not derogate from thoſe of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d. And you ſay farther, that if the King doth not call a Parliament once a Year, He neglects thoſe Laws, and if he delays calling a Parliament in three Years, He neglects the other Law of His own time.</p>
            <p>This renders you an audacious man, that dares thus openly and bare-faced Libel your Prince; but it will never give you the Reputation of a great Lawyer, a good Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, nor a dutiful Subject; for this Argument of yours, is as groſs a Soleciſm, and non-conſequence as any Sophiſter, (to render it more intelligible) any Deceiver ever yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to cheat the World with. And to Demonſtrate it ſo, conſider with your ſelf, If I ſhould make you a Leaſe of a Houſe at the Rent of Twenty pound payable Yearly, and afterwards ſhould make you another Leaſe of the ſame Houſe at Twenty pounds payable once in Three Years; would not you ſay that this laſt Leaſe did diſanul and make void the firſt Leaſe, the making and accepting of a new Leaſe, being a ſurrender in Law of the old one: and whereas by the firſt Leaſe you were to pay Twenty pound every Year, would you not then think your ſelf obliged to pay your Twenty pound but once in three Years? I dare ſay you would; however, you may pay Twenty pound every Year, if you will, notwithſtanding the new Leaſe; and ſo may the King call a Parliament once every Year, or oftner if He pleaſe; but is not nowbound to do ſo by the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106342:5"/>old Statute, any more than you are bound by the old Leaſe, after a new one made of the ſame thing. To make this matter more plain, I will give you another inſtance to this purpoſe, according to what a Reverend Father in the Law ſayes, Examples do not perplex, but clear the point.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe, you and I ſhould make an Agreement in write<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that you ſhould call at my Houſe once a Year; and afterwards by another Agreement, Reciting the former Agreement, whereby you were obliged to call once a Year, we agree that for the future, you ſhall not omit calling once in three Years; Surely, you would not think your ſelf after this laſt Agreement obliged to call every Year.</p>
            <p>Juſt ſo it is in the Kings caſe, as to thoſe Statutes of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3d. for a Statute is but an Agreement between the King and His two Houſes of Parliament; and whereas by the Statute of the 4 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. It is mentioned, that it was Accorded that the Parliament ſhould be holden every Year once, and oftner if need be, and by the Statute of 36. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. to the like effect; &amp; afterwards his now Majeſty and both Houſes of Parliament in the Sixteenth Year of His Reign, come to a new Agreement touching Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, thereby Reciting the ſaid Statutes of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3d. and do Agree that Parliaments ſhall not be diſcontinued above three Years; Doubtleſs, this laſt Statute and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is by Implication of Law a Repeal of the Statutes of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3d. as to calling Parliaments once a Year, and is as much in effect, as if it had been mentioned in the laſt Statute, that notwithſtanding, the ſaid Statutes of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3d. it is ſufficient if the King calls a Parliament once in three Years: and moreover, this laſt Statute, that Parliaments ſhould not be diſcontinued above three Years, had been a vain Statute, as to that particular, if after this was made, the King was ſtill obliged to call a Parliament every year; &amp; it is almoſt Sacriledge in ſome caſes to think
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106342:5"/>that the Parliament ſhould offer any thing that's vain to the King; and by your pardon Sir, there be other maximes in Law, <hi>(viz.) Leges poſteriores priores contraries abrogant,</hi> later Laws differing from the former do make the former void: and <hi>Lex nil fruſtra facit,</hi> the Law, (or if you pleaſe the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Authority) doth nothing in vain; which maximes I muſt tell you had been of better uſe in the Expoſition of thoſe Statutes of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3d. than your notions of a firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Law, for it had been in vain to have made a Statute that required Parliaments every three Years, if they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the other ſhould be inforce: And I conceive it may with better Reaſon be affirmed, that a wilful publiſhing that the King hath neglected the Law, eſpecially when he hath not, is a publiſhing of words to ſtir up the People to a diſlike of His Majeſties Perſon and Government; and in my judgment affirms you an Offender within the Statute of 13 <hi>Ca.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. though you very confidently, like the reſt of your Gang, in the cloſe of your darling Poſtſcript, ſay you were moved to what is there ſet down, by nothing but a hearty Love and Affection to the King; but I hope neither His Majeſty, nor any of His Loyal Subjects will believe you nor them any more.</p>
            <p>To convince you further of your Error, that the King hath not neglected thoſe Laws of <hi>Edw</hi> the 3d. as to calling Parliaments, for by the firſt of the Laws, that is, the 4. of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3d. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. It is not abſolutely required, that a Parliament ſhould be held once every Year, but it is condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally, if need ſhould require; which you deceitfully omit to mention in the charge upon the King, for you well knew it was the King was the judge when need required a Parliament: and this may the better appear, becauſe from the next Year that Statute was made, <hi>viz.</hi> that 5. of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the 3d. there was a diſcontinuance of Parliaments un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the 9th. and the other Act of the 36 of <hi>Edw.</hi> the 3d.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106342:6"/>
               <hi>cap.</hi> 10. ſayes Parliaments ſhall be held once a Year, as at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other time was ordained that is, under the ſame condition as the other Statute was; but perhaps after all this you may be that Fool, that though bray'd in a Morter, would not forſake his folly.</p>
            <p>The next thing I have taken notice of in your Poſtſcript, and which I ſuppoſe was the main matter and drift thereof, (and to maintain it, you have uſed the beſt of your skill) is another Concluſion of yours drawn, I dare ſay, (for your Credit be it known) only from your own mere natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts and notions; for I am ſure it cannot be either from Divine Precept or Example, Humane Experience of paſt Ages, nor the preſent practice of any conſiderable part of the World, of which I have taken ſome conſideration, and it is that which you ſet down in <hi>page</hi> the 43. of the Poſtſcript line the 14. that the Succeſſion of the Crown is Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, becauſe the People ſo appointed it, would have it ſo, or conſented to have it ſo, yet (as you ſay) in a particular Caſe, for ſaving the Nation forſooth, when (by the by it is in no danger) the whole Line and Monarchy it ſelf may be altered by the unlimited power of the Legiſlative Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: but Suppoſe the Nation were in ſuch danger as you ſay (which I ſhall manifeſt to the World it is not.) I hope no King of <hi>England</hi> (which you your ſelf admit to have a part in the Legiſlative Authority) will ever make a Law (though the Parliament ſhould deſire it) either to alter the Government of Monarchy in this Kingdom, nor the Succeſſion thereof, till they ſee the Nation cannot be ſaved without it, or find greater Cauſe and better Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for it than the World ever yet produced; though your Fools Bolt Sir is already ſhot, but hath miſſed the mark you aimedat: And I hope will ever do ſo.</p>
            <p>In order to maintain your Aſſertions, you inveigh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly againſt thoſe that affirm Kingly Government to be of Divine Right and Inſtitution; for which I muſt ſay, the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106342:6"/>World affords more Arguments, and far more convincing than any you have Coyn'd againſt it. However I will add my mite to the Mint, and more than that, I dare enter the Liſts to maintain it againſt you that Kingly Government, yea Hereditary Kingly Government, is the only Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Divine Inſtitution in the World.</p>
            <p>My Reaſons for it ſhall follow, but in the firſt place I will propoſe you are no Atheiſt, and that you will not deny but that God is the Supream King and Governour of all things, and that he takes ſome care of the World, and knows beſt by what ways and methods to Govern it, and that what he ordains is of Divine Inſtitution; for it is a maxim in Logick, <hi>quod contra negantem Principium non eſt diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum,</hi> There's no Reaſoning with ſuch as will not admit fundamental Truths, no more than any buildings (unleſs Caſtles in the Air) can be raiſed without laying a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Theſe premiſes being admitted, which I know you will not gainſay, whatever you think, I would repreſent to your obſervation, that when God had that great Work to do, both to govern and deliver out of Captivity his, own peculiar People the <hi>Jews,</hi> and to redeem them out of the power of a mighty King, he choſe them a King, <hi>Moſes,</hi> who none will deny to be a King, that knows what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Office and Power of a King; although he was not named a King, for he as only Supream under God by Gods own appointment (not by the Peoples Election) exerciſed all the Offices of a King over that People, he was their chief Captain, and their chief Judge, and ſo were all his Succeſſors after him that went by the name of Judges, they were Kings and Soveraigns in their turns, and were then called Judges; as I conceive <hi>propter Excellentiam,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the chief part of a Kings Office by himſelf and his Deputies to Adminiſter Juſtice between his Subjects:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106342:7"/>and in thoſe dayes, and long before, moſt Kings were called Judges; though of latter times the word is applicable to the inferiour Magiſtrates only. God himſelf is called the Judge of all the Earth, as well as the King of Kings.</p>
            <p>That the Judges of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that ſucceeded <hi>Moſes</hi> might as well have been called Kings as Judges, will plainly appear if we conſider the ſignification of the word King, and the Offices and Powers exerciſed by thoſe Judges; as to the word King, it ſignifies him that hath the higheſt Power and Command in a Countrey, and thoſe Judges in their turns, and but one at once and during his life, exerciſed all the power of a King, they commanded the Officers of the people and judged <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And I would alſo note unto you, that moſt of them were choſen by God himſelf, and but very rarely by the people, and when ever they did uſurp upon Gods Prerogative in that particular; as they did when of their own accord they choſe <hi>Abimeleck</hi> the baſe Son of <hi>Jerubbaal,</hi> it ſoon happened that they fell a Butchering one another, and thereby reduced themſelves to ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſtate for want of a Rightfully Conſtituted King or Judge that they were brought to the brink of Ruin; and ſo it happen'd to them alwayes when they tranſgreſſed in that nature: but ſtill upon Recantation, and ſeeking to God he would vouchſafe to chooſe them a King then called a Judge, and whilſt they could keep ſuch a Judge they did well enough. Yet after a little Proſperity they were ſtill apt to return to their licentious Liberty, and after this rate did they continue for about Four hundred Years; but at length it was brought to that paſs by their perverſe ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceitedneſs that God had quite forſaken them: and whereas formerly God did often Converſe with their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (as one man doth with another by word of mouth) and directed them, they rejected his directions and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only on their own Policy, ſo that God withdrew his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106342:7"/>favour from them for a long time. And in the Third of the firſt of <hi>Samuel</hi> you will find it Recorded, that there was no open Viſion in thoſe days, but in a while after God was pleaſed to Reveal himſelf again to <hi>Samuel,</hi> and to adviſe him how to Retrive and Govern thoſe almoſt loſt People. And foraſmuch as ſoon after they asked for a King, and that it is there ſaid, that God was angry with them for it, and foraſmuch as that paſſage is made uſe of by ſome as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt Kingly Government, I cannot omit ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto you, that God was not againſt their having any King at all, but the diſpleaſure was, becauſe they would at that very time have another Governour or King than God had ſet over them, which was <hi>Samuel.</hi> Such a Feeble old man as he, according to their underſtanding, was not fit to Govern them, they did not at all regard it, that God was with him. And this was the cauſe of the Anger, as appears by the ſequel of the Story; For ſays God to <hi>Samuel,</hi> They have not rejected thee, but me have they rejected. And this I do the more firmly believe to be the true meaning of that paſſage and reaſon of Gods Anger, for God deſigned long before that time that they ſhould have a King, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſhould be Governed by a Kingly Government; though you ſay <hi>page</hi> 36. That it was a Government of their own choice, for in <hi>Numb.</hi> 24, verſe the 7. The Prophet <hi>Balaam</hi> foretelling the proſperity of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſays that the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould be higher than <hi>Agag</hi> the King of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. verſe 14. God gives <hi>Iſrael</hi> theſe Directions, When thou art come into the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, verſe 15. <hi>thou ſhalt in any wiſe ſet him King over thee whom the Lord thy God ſhall chooſe,</hi> not whom they would themſelves: with Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in that Chapter, how their King ſhould behave himſelf and his Sons after him; ſo that if there had not been a King deſigned for them by God himſelf, ſometime or other
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106342:8"/>that Propheſie of the Prophet <hi>Balaam</hi> could never have been fulfilled, and the Directions who ſhould be King, and how he was to behave himſelf, and upon what terms he and his Sons after him were to enjoy the Crown had been in vain; whereby it is moſt manifeſt that the mere deſiring of a King as ſome would have it was not the fault, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring a new King at an undue time, deſiring a King, not chooſing one themſelves, which had they done, had been a greater fault by much.</p>
            <p>Another Reaſon that makes me of belief, that the meer asking of a King, had it been at a due time, had been no Offence; becauſe God was not long angry, nor did he long withſtand their deſires, but ſoon after commanded <hi>Samuel</hi> to hearken to the people and give them a King; but this King was to be of Gods chooſing, not of their own choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as you falſely affirm, <hi>page</hi> 36. for God himſelf told <hi>Samuel</hi> that <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould be the man, and cauſed him to be Anointed before the people knew ought thereof, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God directed the Lot according to his own Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and fore-appointment; and when <hi>Samuel</hi> preſented him to the people as choſe by God, they made no more ado but ſubmitted to the choice, <hi>and ſhouted and cryed, God ſave the King;</hi> yet ſome Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> there were in thoſe days that did not like the choice, all which proceedings you may find in the Eighth of the firſt of <hi>Samuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> being thus Eſtabliſhed, and a Succeſſor thought of, for as yet the Succeſſion of Monarchy was not ſettled: <hi>Samuel</hi> by Gods ſpecial appointment, and of his own meer motion without any Requeſt from the people, choſe <hi>David</hi> to be <hi>Sauls</hi> Succeſſor, and in him did God make Monarchy Hereditary, and Eſtabliſhed it ſo as you may ſee in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Samuel</hi> 7.12. by ſaying to <hi>David</hi> in this manner, <hi>when thy days be fulfilled, and thou ſhalt ſleep with thy Fathers, I will ſet up thy Seed after thee;</hi> and verſe the 16. <hi>thy Houſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106342:8"/>and thy Kingdom ſhall be Eſtabliſhed before me for ever,</hi> and in another place, <hi>the Scepter ſhall not depart from</hi> Judah <hi>until</hi> Shiloe <hi>come.</hi> Here's no Proviſo, that the people ſhould alter the Succeſſion; that was to be done by none but God himſelf or by his ſpecial Command, a clear inſtance whereof ſoon happened, for when <hi>David</hi> was Bed-ridden as it were, and every day expected Death; <hi>Adonijah</hi> one of <hi>Davids</hi> Sons by the Mother of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> Exalted himſelf, ſaying <hi>I will be King,</hi> 1ſt. of the 1ſt. of Kings, <hi>and prepared him Chariots and Horſes, and Fifty men to run before him, and made great Feaſts,</hi> at which the people and Captains of the Hoſts cryed, <hi>God ſave King</hi> Adonijah; yet God and old <hi>David</hi> ſaid <hi>Solomon</hi> ſhould be King, and was ſo; wherein is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable this thing further, that God who foreknew without doubt that <hi>Solomon</hi> in his latter days would ſet up Idolatry; yet he did not puniſh him beforehand, he did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſentence againſt him, that the Kingdom ſhould be rended from him; nor was there any Bill of Excluſion againſt him, until he had actually committed the Offence, which Offence was not only that himſelf privately had Committed Idolatry; but that he had alſo publickly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the people thereunto, by ſetting up high places to ſacrifice to <hi>Kemoſh</hi> and <hi>Moloch</hi> as appeareth in the Eleventh of the Firſt of <hi>Kings;</hi> and pray note further, when this ſentence came to be Executed, and ten Tribes were given to <hi>Jereboam,</hi> there was not a blow ſtruck on either ſide, from whence you may take notice by the by, that God did not require the aſſiſtance of Rebellion or Seditious ſcriblers to effect thoſe works, and it cannot be ſaid that Gods Arm is ſhortned now more than at other times.</p>
            <p>I conceive Gods Example is as obliging as his Precepts, and that if we imitate him, we ſhall never do amiſs; it is therefore Argument ſufficient that Monarchy, yea Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Monarchy is moſt agreeable to his will of any Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106342:9"/>whatſoever, becauſe he Eſtabliſhed it himſelf amongſt his own peculiar people, and ſince he did ſo, and ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently commanded Obedience to it, I wonder how any man can ſay that Hereditary Monarchy is not of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution: or having ſaid ſo, can ſuppoſe he ſhould be believed; and methinks you your ſelf ſeem diffident that there would not be much credit given to your Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, and therefore you make Proviſion as well as you can againſt the univerſal approbation and embracing of that ſort of Government; and would endeavour to make the World believe it was a Government peculiar to the <hi>Jews</hi> only, for you ſay page the 36. That the <hi>Jews</hi> form of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ought with leſs Reaſon to be the rule of all Kingly Governours, becauſe it was a Government choſen by themſelves; than the Laws of the <hi>Jews</hi> ought to be the Laws of all Nations which they are not. Theſe are the words of the Poſtſcript.</p>
            <p>I have already ſhewed, that you were miſtaken in affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Monarchical Government of the <hi>Jews</hi> was of their own chooſing, for it was of Gods chooſing; and as to your intimating that the Laws of the <hi>Jews</hi> ought not to be the Laws of all Nations; there you ought to have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, for though the Law of not eating Swines fleſh was only peculiar to thoſe people in reſpect of the Climate they lived in, for that it inclined the Inhabitants of that Countrey to Leproſie, and therefore was never intended to be an univerſal Law; and the Ceremonial Law of the <hi>Jews</hi> is now out of doors, becauſe it conſiſted of Types of Chriſt coming, who is now come, and therefore the Types of his coming are uſeleſs; yet the Moral Law of God the Ten Commandements which were Laws to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ought to be Laws all the World over, and are ſo taken, and they are Everlaſting and Immutable as well as univerſal Laws; but there is no Rational conſequence in your Argument, if
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106342:9"/>I ſhould admit that all the Laws of the <hi>Jews</hi> had been pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to themſelves only, for though their Laws might not be Laws for all the World to follow, yet Gods method in enforcing the <hi>Jews</hi> to obedience to theſe Laws, might up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on good reaſon be thought a good precedent to be followed to enforce obedience to other Laws.</p>
            <p>There is a great difference between Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though you ſeem to make the ſame Rule for both, for Laws are Rules for men to walk by, and Government is the exerciſe of the means and methods to enforce men to walk by thoſe Rules; and though ſome Laws of one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey may not be convenient for another; yet the means and method to enforce obedience to thoſe Laws which are beſt, are the beſt; the Ore in all Countreys is not alike good, but that which is the Univerſal beſt way of refining it, is ſo, whether the refining be in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland;</hi> ſo that if the <hi>Jews</hi> were beſt Governed according to their Laws by an Hereditary Monarchy, I can ſee no reaſon why the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould not be beſt Govern'd according to their Laws by an Hereditary Monarchy alſo.</p>
            <p>It is not only God's example in governing the particular people the <hi>Jews,</hi> but they are his general Precepts that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate his good liking of Monarchy all the World over, for <hi>fear God,</hi> and <hi>honour the King,</hi> are general and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Commands not limited nor reſtrained to any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Place or People, and they have ſo cloſe a Connexion, and are plac'd ſo near together, that it ſeems to imply as much as that, if you fear God you will honour the King, and that God requires the one from us as well as the other: many places of Holy Writ requires our obedience to Kings as Supream, and to Governours under them, but I find not a tittle that requires obedience to any other ſort of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment where there is not a King, I find no approbation of ſuch as the Kingleſs Keepers of the Liberty of <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106342:10"/>or other place; <hi>Hogen-Mogen</hi> States of the United Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Burgo-Maſters of <hi>Venice</hi> or <hi>Geneva,</hi> or ſuch like; ſuch Governments ſeem to be quite out of Gods care or regard, and therefore not to be regarded by good men, nor to be look'd upon to be of Divine Inſtitution, having neither Divine Precept nor Example to Countenance them.</p>
            <p>But though I take Monarchy to be Hereditary by Divine Appointment, yet I cannot believe that any man of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, unleſs it be ſuch an enemy as ſowed Tares in the Wheat, or ſome falſe friend that will affirm that by Divine Right and Inſtitution, a King may Tyrannize over his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or impoſe unreaſonable and unjuſt things upon them for Law; but I humbly conceive Kings are obliged to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Laws of God and Nature, and are bound truly, and it is their duty to govern according to thoſe Laws, and the Laws Rightfully made by themſelves and Predeceſſors, which are not contrary to the Laws of God, as you may ſee in the forementioned 17. of <hi>Deut.</hi> and very plentifully in Scripture elſewhere: but if a King breaks any of thoſe Laws, he is not puniſhable by his Subjects, but God aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes that to himſelf, and it is ſufficient puniſhment, for it is a woful caſe to fall into the hand of the Lord when angry.</p>
            <p>Deſcend we now to Natural Reaſon, and conſider what that dictates to us in this matter, it being ſufficiently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, that Monarchy is of Divine Inſtitution by what is before-mentioned, but put caſe there were nothing touching it in Divinity one way or other, hath not the experience and practice of the World for ſome thouſand of years in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd us, that an Hereditary Monarchy is the beſt ſort of Government for the People, in reference to the ſupport of Human Society? Have not all Philoſophers and Politicians of any note left their Opinions to poſterity that it is ſo? Hath not Monarchy been the ſetled Government of this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106342:10"/>Kingdom for ſo many Centuries of years? And are not our Chronicles ſo plain in the point, that no conſiderable miſchief ever befell us but by interrupting Hereditary Succeſſion of the Crown, and that that miſchief hath been of no leſs conſequence than the ruin of the then Inhabitants? and ſhall ſuch Muſhrooms as you pretend to ſay, that not only the Line of Succeſſion but Monarchy it ſelf may be alter'd? becauſe ſuch Ignoramus's in Politicks know no other way of ſaving a Nation from drowning but by caſting it into the fire? We have had warning ſufficient, I hope not to be gul'd with any ſuch whim whams any more. But becauſe nothing leſs at preſent than the alteration of the Succeſſion or of Monarchy it ſelf would ſerve your turn to keep out Popery, I will for your ſatisfaction, if it be poſſible, and if your underſtanding and honeſty will bear it, make it plain, in a few words that we are as ſafe and ſecure againſt Popery, as the Art of man can make us, and that we want nothing but what is Gods own work to ſecure us from Popery ſo long as we ſtick cloſe to and maintain the Hereditary Succeſſion of the Crown, though we ſhould happen to ſee a Popiſh Succeſſor; and the way to perfect the work and to prevail with God to do what doth belong to him, is by Prayers and Penitence, not by Sedition and Rebellion.</p>
            <p>If ever Popery ſhould be eſtabliſht in <hi>England,</hi> I ſpeal in reference to what lies in the power of men, it muſt be either by Military force or by Law, the Military force muſt be either home force, or foreign force; by home force it can never be, though the King were a Papiſt, becauſe the whole Nation is averſe to it, and very violent againſt it except a very inconſiderable number who if they ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the leaſt look that way, they would be devoured, as a hungry Lyon would devour a new fallen Lamb, and as to foreign force the only way to ſubject us to it, is to divide us
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106342:11"/>into two conſiderable Parties, and then to engage us in the Slaughter of each other, which would moſt aſſuredly be the conſequence of ſetting a ſide of any of the Royal Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from their turn of Succeſſion. And of this the Kingdom can give many ſad inſtances; I ſhall mention only that of Depoſing <hi>Richard</hi> II. and ſetling the Crown upon <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, though by Act of Parliament, and with <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the Second's ſeeming (but forc'd) conſent, which produced ſuch miſerable Wars between the Heirs and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers of both Kings, as rendred the Kingdom a meer Slaughter-houſe for the moſt part of fourſcore years, in which time the number of the ſlain is uncertain, but if we may gueſs at <hi>Hercules</hi>'s body by the length of his foot, their number muſt be very vaſt, for I find there was ſlain upon that occaſion in one Battle thirty ſix thouſand ſeven hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, threeſcore and ſixteen Perſons; and all the Arts and Acts of Parliament afterwards, which were many, and which played handy-dandy with the Crown, acting it one while upon one, then upon another, could never ſettle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs till it had pleas'd God to do it by ordering the matter ſo, that the Heirs of both Families were, one of them a Man, and the other a Woman, and that theſe did marry one another whoſe Nuptial Feaſts lull'd the Nation into a pacifick ſlumber, and put an end to thoſe unhappy Troules, and <hi>England</hi> once again enjoy'd a bleſſed peace, until ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unparallel'd Uſurpation upon the Crown, by the ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſanctified Parliament in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt his time, which can never be forgot, though you are angry it is not. Theſe Inſtances ſhould be caution enough to any reaſonable men, not to invade Gods Prerogative, and interrupt the Hereditary Succeſſion of the Crown, but leave it to its due and eſtabliſh'd courſe of Deſcent.</p>
            <p>I am confident ſcarce any man of ſenſe believes but that if ever hereafter (in our days eſpecially) it ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106342:11"/>that the next in Suceeſſion to the Crown by courſe of deſcent ſhould be put by, though by Act of Parliament it would produce as ſad effects as ever it did; and it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable but our Popiſh Neighbours (who are more Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent now than ever) would lay hold on ſuch an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: the <hi>French</hi> King, as I am credibly inform'd, having now a ſtanding and eſtabliſhed Army of two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men or more, how eaſie then would it be for him, when we had mangled, torn and deſtroyed the greateſt part of our ſelves, to make himſelf Maſter of the wearied ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Party, and then Impoſe upon them his own Popiſh Religion? So that to me nothing ſeems ſo ready a way to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce Popery as altering the Succeſſion of the Crown out of its Lineal Courſe of Deſcent, unleſs it be by ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conventicles, where men teach, and the ſcrupulous Brotherhood learn with greedineſs any manner of Doctrine, ſpecially the lawfulneſs of King-killing, and Rebellion, to propagate their Hereſies, Sects and Schiſms.</p>
            <p>Hence I may ſay, it is very evident that by force of Arms Popery can never be ſetled here ſo long as the Succeſſion of the Crown is kept in the due courſe of Deſcent, and it may be made as manifeſtly appear, that it can never be introduc'd by Law, though there were a Popiſh Succeſſor; for though the King be the Law-maker, yet his power is ſo limited and reſtrained by the Law of Uſage and Cuſtom, that he can make no new Law without the conſent of his Parliament; and the Law as it is, is Proviſional enough to prevent the Papiſts acting to any prejudice. For as the Law now is, no man is to be a Member in either Houſe of Parliament unleſs he upon Oath renounce Popery, and take the Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance and Supremacy; nor can any man practiſe the Law, Phyſick, Chyrurgery, the Art of an Apothecary, or any Liberal Science for gain, unleſs he renounce Popery, and take the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy: No man can
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106342:12"/>be Ordained a Miniſter of the Goſpel, or permitted to Preach in a Church, unleſs he Renounce Popery; but at a Conventicle be he Papiſt or be he Turk, or Jew, or what he will, he may Preach there any manner of Doctrine, and the People are angry if they be interrupted. So that we are in danger of being taught no Popery in Pulpits, unleſs among the Lawleſs Conventicles, whoſe Teachers, if the Law be put in Execution againſt their Diſciples, will have but few Hearers; and if all this be not enough his Majeſty was Graciouſly pleaſed to aſſure us that he would make any new Law to ſecure us from Popery: Yea, even to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining of a Popiſh Succeſſor, ſo that the Succeſſion of the Crown were not put out of its Lineal Courſe of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, and I dare ſay the great Gown-man whoever he was whoſe Opinion (as ſome ſay) ſo far ſway'd the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, that they thought no Law could ſufficiently ſecure us againſt a ſuppoſed Popiſh Succeſſor, but Excluſion from the Succeſſion, could not really be of that mind; for a King can do no great harm, he is but one man, and if he ſhould in his own Perſon attempt to offer any unjuſt violence to any man, it is an eaſie matter to fly from him, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out imputation of Cowardiſe, it being upon no account juſtifiable to reſiſt the Kings Perſon with force, but if any man (Officer or other) ſhould by the Kings Command, kill, wound or beat any man that doth not obſtinately refuſe to anſwer his charge by courſe of Law, before he is Convict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Fact by Verdict of his Peers or Equals, or by his own Confeſſion, and before he is ſentenc'd by a Judg for that purpoſe lawfully Authoriſed; he that ſhould ſo do, is puniſhable notwithſtanding ſuch Command: and moreover though the King by his Prerogative Royal may lawfully cauſe any man to be Impriſoned in order to come to Tryal yet if in the Commitment it appear not to be for Treaſon or Felony ſpecially nam'd, he muſt be bayl'd by the Judg
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106342:12"/>and though Impriſon'd for any of thoſe offences, yet he is to continue in Priſon but until he may be Try'd by due Courſe of Law; but unto the Kings Legal Commands in a Judicial way, the whole Strength and Power of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is bound to aſſiſt in compelling Obedience thereunto, be his Commands ſignified by Himſelf or by his Magiſtrates and Judges in his Name, who are ſworn to do therein as the Law requires, and not otherwiſe, ſo that the King hath all Power to do lawful things lawfully; yet to do any thing illegally, he hath ſo little Power, that it is truly ſaid the King can do no wrong: and beſides all this, every King at his Coronation takes an Oath to confirm the Laws to his People, to maintain the Goſpel eſtabliſhed in the Kingdom, to keep Peace, execute Juſtice, and grant the Commons their rightful Cuſtoms (be his own Religion what it will.) So that here's all the Bars and Bolts imaginable to keep out Popery from being impoſed on the People of <hi>England,</hi> whatever the Kings Religion be, which thoſe do not well conſider, that compare theſe days with thoſe of Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which were long before any of theſe Laws before-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned were made, and when Reformation was but ſcarce begun by her Father towards the later end of his Reign, and countenanced, but not much improv'd by her Brother who died an Infant King; and when that Queen came to the Crown, it cannot be ſuppoſed that the tenth part of the Nation were Converts from Popery, as appears by what then hapned, for ſhe ſoon got a Popiſh Parliament, who as ſoon ſubmitted themſelves to the Pope, and asked Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for their offences againſt him, and declared themſelves ready to abrogate all Laws prejudicial to the See of <hi>Rome:</hi> but the Caſe is alter'd now. Here's no Popiſh Members can be elected, the whole Nation being almoſt Proteſtants, and conſequently will elect no Papiſt, nor one ſuſpected to be ſo; or if any ſuch ſhould chance to be ſo elected, yet no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106342:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106342:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106342:14"/>ſuch Popiſh Member is to be admitted into Parliament. So, here's no Popiſh Parliament can be that ſhould conſent to make Laws in ſavour of Popery, nor can there be any Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Magiſtrates admitted that ſhould favour the Papiſts by omitting to execute the Laws againſt them. Nor is there any Prieſts that ſhould perſwade them to Popery to be heard among us, unleſs in Conventicles; ſo that here's no room by Law for Popery ſure in <hi>England,</hi> nor ever can be if we keep to the courſe we are in, and gape not after chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the Government, or ſuffer our ſelves to be frighted with ſhadows, ſo far as to depend more upon diſhoneſt Policy than Gods Providence and honeſt Prudence.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that Originally the Succeſſion of the Crown were in the people; yet in the ſame breath you contradict your ſelf, by ſaying, it is ſo now; for you ſay alſo, that they have appointed and conſented that it ſhould be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary. Is not a Bargain a Bargain? Do you think they can Revoke this Agreement at pleaſure? I think there is no Law for that.</p>
            <p>That the people of <hi>England,</hi> both in this and former Ages as far as an Oath Eſtabliſhed by Act of Parliament can oblige, (which I think no man will ſay, but it is the greateſt obligation in the World) have or ought to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound themſelves that the Succeſſion of the Crown ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Hereditary.</p>
            <p>The Oath of Allegiance Eſtabliſhed (by the Legiſlative <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uthority in your own Notion) and by the Statute 3. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c.</hi> and 4. and elſewhere, ſo frequently obliged to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ken, is in theſe words, <hi>viz. That we will bear faith and true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llegiance to his Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors, and him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d them will defend to the utmoſt of our power againſt all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nſpiracies and Attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ainſt his or their perſons,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106342:14"/>
            <p>Now for a little Expoſition upon the Text, for nothing can be ſo plain, but ſome may invert the ſenſe of it, ſince ſome wreſt even the Scriptures to their own Damnation, and yet go according to their Conſciences ſtill, ſuch as their nature is, ſuch is their Logick: the <hi>Spider</hi> draws Poyſon from the ſame Flower that the <hi>Bee</hi> gathers Honey.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall obſerve only, That the Statute which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points this Oath of Allegiance was made ſince the Statute of the 13. of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which made it an Offence to ſay the Queen by Authority of Parliament could not limit the Deſcent of the Crown, and if the ſaid Statute that appoints the ſaid Oath, by ſuch appointment, hath ſo limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſetled the Deſcent and Succeſſion of the Crown, that I cannot perceive how now it can be juſtly altered: for demonſtration whereof it is requiſite, the ſignification of the word <hi>Heirs</hi> be rightfully underſtood; this word Heirs, is in our Engliſh Dialect the ſame the Latins called, <hi>Heredes Sanguinis,</hi> Heirs of the Blood, not adopted Heirs, ſtill the next of kin to the Deceaſed Succeſſively one after the other for ever; for though a Father ſhould give away his Eſtate from his Eldeſt Son; yet he is Heir, though a diſinherited one, and though men diſpoſe of their Lands as they think fit: Yet, <hi>Deus facit Haeredes,</hi> God makes Heirs; and I take the meaning of the word Heirs in that Oath to be no other than the next of Kin to the deceaſed King, and the joyning of Succeſſors to Heirs is capable of, (or at leaſtwiſe in the common ſenſe and underſtanding thereof, which is the ſenſe it ought to be taken there, can have) no other conſtruction, but that the Kings Heirs ſhall be his Succeſſors for ever, and that we ſhall pay the ſame Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to the Kings Heirs in their turns, as we do to them; but you ſay the unlimited power of the Legiſlative Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity can do any thing, alter Succeſſion, yea Monarchy it ſelf
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106342:15"/>even at the very day that you wrote the Poſtſcript; without Controverſie the power of the Legiſlative Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is very great, but I muſt diſtinguiſh between what may be done, and what may be juſtly done. If Monarchy or the Succeſſion thereof ſhould be altered by the Legiſlative power, as it was by a Part of the Legiſlative Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in diſmal 48. and as is apparent ſome wiſh it ſhould again; It doth not therefore follow, that it ſhould be juſt to do ſo any more; for whatſoever is contrary to the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Law of God, though commanded by the Legiſlative Authority, is unjuſt: and though the Legiſlative Authority may be of that power and force as to compel Obedience to their Laws; yet they can never make Vice a Vertue, or give Sanctity to a thing that is <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> evil in it's very nature and eſſence.</p>
            <p>By the Oath of Allegiance we declare, that we do plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſincerely ſwear according to the expreſs words there ſet down; and according to the plain and common ſenſe and underſtanding of theſe words. If ſo, by <hi>Heirs</hi> there, muſt be meant, the ſame that is meant thereby according to the common ſenſe, in common diſcourſe; and according to that ſenſe then, by Heirs is meant the next of Kin; for when we enquire who is ſuch a mans Heir, we mean who is next of Kin to him. But oh, ſay you and the new-true Proteſtants, the Succeſſion of the Crown was not intended to be ſo abſolutely limited to the Heirs, but that if the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament thought fit to appoint another that is not the real Heir, he muſt be the man.</p>
            <p>This is a very vain idle and empty Hypotheſis, and a meer groundleſs ſuppoſition, for the Oath it ſelf reſtrains the meaning of the words to their common ſenſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and renounces all manner of mental evaſion or reſervation whatſoever: ſo here's no reſervation for an
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106342:15"/>objection againſt the Heir, neither as to his Religion or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>Here I have ſhewed you Gods Example of Eſtabliſhing an Hereditary Monarchy, and his precepts to obey it; in no place in Divinity, do I find a power given from God to the people to alter it at pleaſure, or when they think fit upon any pretence whatſoever; here's alſo an Oath of Obedience required by Act of Parliament from all people to ſtand to, and defend the Hereditary Succeſſion of the Crown; here's alſo in that Oath a Renuntiation of all Pardons and Abſolutions from that Oath: and an Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that it is to be underſtood according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe and meaning of the words, and this Oath is on ought to be taken by all people in the Kingdom: How ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifiable then would it be in the Legiſlative power to Act Counter to all theſe, and having once required us to ſwear fidelity to an Hereditary Succeſſor, and to renounce all Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions from that Oath; yet after wards to compel us to ſwear fidelity to one that is not the Hereditary Succeſſor? <hi>Dic quibus in terris &amp; eris mihi magnus Apollo,</hi> from ſuch Legiſlative power as deſpiſe Gods Example, Reject his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and will engage a whole Nation to forſwear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves rather than uſe other means to Reſtrain even a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Succeſſor, <hi>Good Lord deliver me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to this point of Succeſſion, I ſhall add what I find Recommended by Mr. <hi>Prin</hi> in his Preface to <hi>Cottons</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, <hi>fol.</hi> 10. Obſerve 14 Kings (ſays he) Created and ſet up merely by Parliaments and their own power in them without any true Hereditary Title, have ſeldom anſwered the Lords and Commons Expectations in the preſervation of their juſt Laws, Liberties and Anſwers to Petitions; yea themſelves branded at laſt for Tyrants, Traytors, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers</p>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:106342:16"/>
            <p>ſuch another Doom, as the ambitious Tower-Builders had, confuſion of Tongues, yea and Senſes to.</p>
            <p>And as to the Scrupulous Brotherhood, Recommend me to them, and let them know, that I dare affirm their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are moſt of them Jeſuits; the true Papiſts in Maſque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, who inſtead of Preaching Peace, incite the people by a ſide-wind to Rebellion: and let them know alſo, That I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know of thoſe ſeeming tender Conſcienced Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters what Anſwer they will make at the great Tribunal, when it ſhall be askt them why they occaſioned the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of their King, put three Nations together by the Ears, made them ſuck each others Hearts blood out, Rob, Raviſh and Burn? for that hath once been the conſequence of their Scrupuloſity, and may be ſo again, if they be not prevented. Do you and they think it will be a ſufficient excuſe to ſay, we could not hear a man Preach in white ſleeves; we had more kindneſs for one in a little round Cloak; we could not look upon the Miniſter making the ſign of the Croſs in Baptiſm, or we were loth leſt we ſhould ſpoil our ſilk Stockings, to kneel at the Sacrament; for our Conſciences told us, he was the finer man that Pray'd and Preach'd without Book, by the help of the Spirit (whither good or bad) than he that well weighed and conſidered what he ſhould ſay before he ſpoke, though we are commanded not to be haſty to utter any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God. Sure theſe reaſons will never excuſe them; the rather for that they themſelves acknowledge that they are but indifferent things in their, own nature wherein they diſſent from the Government; and being ſo, they are the more to blame that diſſent, and there is greater reaſon that they ſhould comply with the Government, than that the Government ſhould truckle to every Humoriſt: You ſay well, in that you ſay there is nothing more expoſeth the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106342:16"/>Authority of Government to contempt, than a publick and open neglect of its Injunctions; therefore I do heartliy wiſh our Magiſtrates would uſe civil force and power as far as by Law they may, to enforce Obedience to the Laws both in Church and State; and like good wiſe Parents give their ſtubborn Children the Rod of Correction in due time before they grow too head-ſtrong.</p>
            <p>I had almoſt omitted to ſay any thing touching Uſurpers, which I conceive may be very material, for it is not enough to know who hath right to the Crown at the Deceaſe of a King: but it behoves us alſo to know how to prevent or remove Uſurpers, in caſe any ſuch ſhould happen, and for that purpoſe I cannot but inform you, that in my reading I find mention made of two ſorts of Tyrannical Monarchs; one ſort of Tyrant is he who of his own Authority taketh upon him the Soveraignty by the Aſſiſtance of ſome looſe irregular Party, without right, and this ſort of Tyrant is he who by the Laws and Writings of the Ancients is commanded to be kil'd, with promiſe of ample Rewards to ſuch as ſhould do it; in this caſe making no difference, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be a good man or a wicked one, for it is not lawful for any man living of himſelf, or by the Aſſiſtance or incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any Factions or diſcontented Party, without good right to invade the Soveraignty, and to make himſelf Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his fellows; what colour ſoever of Vertue, Juſtice, Religion or Reformation he pretends, in plain Engliſh he deſerves the worſt of Deaths that doth it. In this only caſe it is lawful to proceed according to the Courſe once known in <hi>England</hi> by the name of <hi>Abbington</hi>-Law, that is to hang them firſt, and try them after. And this manner of proceeding in caſe of an Uſurper was once Eſtabliſhed by Law among the <hi>Romans</hi> by the name of the Law <hi>Valeria;</hi> and thereby leave was given to every man to ſlay ſuch
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106342:17"/>Tyrant without Tryal. For in ſuch a caſe to proceed by way of formal Legal Juſtice, the Commonwealth would be conſumed with the Firebrands of Uſurpation before they could be quenched; and beſides, it was impoſſible to bring ſuch formally to Juſtice: for who could in a Judicial way call to account ſuch a one as <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> in the Head of his Conquering Army; therefore it was thought better in ſuch a caſe to ſuppreſs the Tyrant by force, or ſtratagem, rather than by too nice inſiſting upon the Regularities of proceedings by Law, loſe both the Law and the State alſo. And when I conſider this, I cannot but ſay it was much to the diſreputation of the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cavaliers, conſidering how many indigent Officers did appear at his now Majeſties Reſtauration, that none of them had the courage by Dagger or Piſtol, to cut off that Uſurping King-killing Tyrant <hi>NOLL.</hi> But on the other hand, this courſe is by no means juſtifiable but in caſe of an Uſurper, not in caſe of a Sovereign Prince that is lawfully eſtabliſhed and ſetled, or hath right to the Sovereignty either by ſpecial call from God, as <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> or by right of Hereditary Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as the Heirs of the Kings of <hi>England, Spain, France, Turkey, Ruſſia,</hi> and all the Countries of <hi>Africa,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay in ſuch caſes that courſe is by no means to be thought upon, for though perchance (which falls out rarely) that ſuch a lawful Prince forgetting his duty ſhould become beyond meaſure, cruel, covetous and wicked, perverting both the Laws of God and man (which is the other ſort of Tyrant) his Perſon ought by no means to be touch'd, for God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>Touch not my anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The want of making a diſtinction between theſe two ſorts of Tyrants hath led many into great miſtakes, holding it lawful for Subjects to riſe up in Arms againſt any ſort of Tyrant; a concluſion of a moſt dangerous and deſtructive, as well as irreligious, conſequence: For where that Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106342:17"/>hath got any footing, ſeditious and ambitious Men will never fail to ſcandalize the beſt of Princes, thereby to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the People to Rebellion, that theſe few Villains may reap ſome profit to themſelves by the Ruin of multitudes of others; and it hath been often experienced, that Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt a lawful Prince, though ever ſo cruel, hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more miſchief than could poſſibly have hapned had ſuch a one been ſuffered for his time, even in Kingdoms where Kings had more power to do evil than here they have. So that in Human Prudence, as well as in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Divine Precepts, and for our own Oaths ſake, it is moſt ſafe for us to be firm in our Allegiance to our Kings and their Heirs: and as to what may happen upon failure of Heirs, and who then ſhall be Succeſſor, let it alone for thoſe to determine that may be then concern'd; but for my part. I am reſolved not to be forſworn for any Power upon Earth, for I am confident thoſe above will never deſire it. Nay more, God hath ſaid, He <hi>will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his name in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid by our Saviour, That <hi>all ſins ſhall be forgive men, but the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I have often thought wilful Perjury might be the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, not only from the evil conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of it, which is dreadful, but even from the word of the Commandment that forbids it, which ſays, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain,</hi> (which hath this meaning, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſwear falſly by his name</hi> or affirm any thing falſly, and call God to witneſs the truth of it) <hi>for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſs that taketh his name in vain;</hi> which is to be underſtood as if it had ſaid God will not pardon him that taketh his name in vain. And there is not that ſaid of the breakers of any of the other Laws; but this I refer to the Conſideration of your ſelf and the reſt of the Bill of Excluſion-men, and to all other
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106342:18"/>that make ſhipwreck of their Oath, and Conſciences, and let me recommend it unto you, that you pray for the Peace of our <hi>Engliſh Jeruſalem,</hi> for they, and they only that love it, ſhall proſper: And that they may do ſo is my hearty deſire, And when I am convinced you are of that temper, but not until then I ſhall be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend <hi>W. W.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106342:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
